### Contact

(+91)9971060451 (Mobile) ankursharma.iitd@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/ankur-sharma-984166144 (LinkedIn)

## Top Skills

Android Development Java

**Data Structures** 

## Languages

English (Full Professional) Hindi (Native or Bilingual)

### Honors-Awards

Kishore Vaigyanik Protsahan Yojana (KVPY) Fellowship

Regional Mathematics Olympiad Indian National Olympiads SCRA

National Abacus Champion

### **Publications**

Representation Learning on Graphs - A Survey

Anatomy of a Rumour: Social media and the suicide of Sushant Singh Rajput

PickMe - IITD

Ideology Detection in the Indian Mass Media

Price Forecasting & Anomaly Detection of Commodity Prices in India

# **Ankur Sharma**

Researcher at Microsoft Research (MSR) New Delhi

# Summary

Hello,

I am currently working as a research intern at Microsoft Research (MSR) India in the Technology for Emerging Markets (TEM) group for the Social Media Analysis team under the supervision of Joyojeet Pal. My work is centred around analysing the political discourse on Twitter across various states and parties in India. I have graduated with a Dual Degree (B.Tech + M.Tech) in Computer Science and Engineering from the Indian Institute of Technology (IIT), Delhi with specialisation in Applied Machine Learning. My primary research interests lie in the applications of machine learning in the real world to create a positive societal impact by helping people in tackling humanitarian & environmental challenges. Applied Machine Learning entails the need for cross-domain research that spans several related areas in media studies, social science, language, and cognition, amongst others. Apart from this, I have a solid foundation in core computer science including Systems Engineering and Operating Systems. My long-term career plan is to be a researcher in applied machine learning – either in industry or in academia.

Feel free to contact me.

Email: ankursharma.iitd@gmail.com

Github: /ankursharma-iitd

# Experience

Microsoft Research Intern July 2020 - Present (5 months) Bengaluru, Karnataka, India

I'm working with Prof. Joyojeet Pal at Microsoft Research (MSR) India on analysing the twitter feeds of politicians in India and in the US. My recent research projects have been centred around the use of social media platforms in mainstream politics, specifically around political brand building in India.

Indian Institute of Technology, Delhi 1 year 2 months

Teaching Assistant January 2020 - August 2020 (8 months) New Delhi Area, India

I'm currently working as a Teaching Assistant for COL 380 (Parallel & Distributed Programming) Course at IIT Delhi under Prof. Rijurekha Sen.

## Teaching Assistant

July 2019 - December 2019 (6 months)

New Delhi Area, India

I'm a TA for the course - Data Structures & Algorithms (COL 106) under the supervision of Prof. Subodh Kumar, and responsible for managing 350+ students assignments, grading, quizzes, etc.

**HKUST Engineering Masters** Research Delegate July 2019 - July 2019 (1 month)

Selected for an all-expenses paid research summer camp by HKUST Seng School of Enginnering - Elite Student 2019.

Microsoft Software Engineering Intern May 2019 - July 2019 (3 months) Bengaluru Area, India

Worked on Microsoft's Outlook contextual add-ins recommendation system for real time add-ins recommendations while composing/reading email with direct installation and launch integrated platform.

Massachusetts Institute of Technology Visiting Researcher December 2018 - May 2019 (6 months) Cambridge, Massachusetts

I was working on the applications of deep learning & computer vision in wireless networks to articulate pose estimation & activity recognition by leveraging RF signals under the supervision of Prof. Dina Katabi.

Harvard Project for Asian and International Relations (HPAIR) Page 2 of 5

Delegate for Energy & Environmental Sustainability December 2018 - February 2019 (3 months)

Cambridge, Massachusetts

Represented as one of the 300 delegates from all over the world for the HPAIR Harvard College Conference held at Harvard University, USA in Feb 2019

Microsoft Software Engineering Intern May 2018 - July 2018 (3 months)

Bengaluru Area, India

I was working on the storage aspects in the Azure Cluster and specifically working to remove bottlenecks with specific optimizations done at the levels of the file system at each node. The work is pretty interesting and gives an exposure to the cloud computing services which should be efficient and scalable when you are dealing exabytes of data each day.

Received Pre-Placement Offer from Microsoft after the successful completion of summer internship.

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign Research Assistant May 2017 - July 2017 (3 months) Urbana-Champaign, Illinois Area

I was working on a project in the field of Manufacturing Security. The project is intended to protect factory machines from various attackers who try to steal the sensor data and then extract useful information.

The project aims to secure infrastructure hardware(e.g. 3D printing devices) using state-of-the-art cybersecurity methods, and devises strategies to automate the data reconstruction process associated with such attacks. The way this project directly maps physical concepts to theoretical cryptography is quite remarkable.

Assistive Technologies Group Android Developer January 2017 - April 2017 (4 months) Assistech Labs, IIT Delhi

The project was done under the course COP 315 – An Embedded Design project, in IIT Delhi, under Prof. M. Balakrishnan in 2017. We designed a platform comprising of a Desktop IDE, and an android app. The purpose of the project is to assist blind people in reading data from the tactile sheets using an android app which plays the audio of the part corresponding to a click-gesture using real-time finger scanning. To find more about the project, follow the link.

TRYST, IIT Delhi Activity Head, Events January 2017 - March 2017 (3 months)

PickMe - IITD Co-Founder January 2016 - January 2017 (1 year 1 month) New Delhi Area, India

Use PickMe to order a rickshaw at your footstep in this scorching heat. Just pick your phone up, tap a button to get the number and make the call, the rickshaw will come to you. PickMe makes use of GPS to connect you with the nearest three available rickshaws in the IIT Delhi campus. Then you are just one call away. It is fast, simple and works on just one click. The charges are the same as normal rickshaw rates, that is, there is no extra cost for using the app.\*\* Exclusively functional for IIT Delhi

\*\*Now you don't need to walk back from institute area to your hostel, just order a rickshaw. The application is designed to save the hassle of all IITD residents. There is NO EXTRA CHARGE for using the app to call the rickshaw. PickMe is operational at every point inside the campus.

Rendezvous IITD
Team Head
June 2016 - October 2016 (5 months)
IIT Delhi
Publicity

Waste Warriors Android Developer May 2016 - July 2016 (3 months)

Designed a Waste Management Android Application that stores type, and quantity of waste among different blocks of the village, and synchronises this data on the MySQL database online, aiding in quick-data analytics.

## Education

Indian Institute of Technology, Delhi

Dual Degree: Bachelors & Masters, Computer Science and

Engineering (2015 - 2020)

Seth Anandram Jaipuria School Class XII, CBSE · (2013 - 2015)

St. Mary's Convent School Class X, ICSE · (2007 - 2012)